Today I've got something special to share.
I just received this kit in the mail which
includes this chip which is likely different
from any other you've come across before,
because this chip is the first of its
kind to be made publicly available.
It's custom-manufactured using over 150 distinct
designs submitted by an open source community.
The designs on this chip are not
just from seasoned professionals,
they're also from enthusiasts, hobbyists,
and total beginners of all ages.
If you're one of the people whose
design is included on this chip,
congratulations! And thank you for contributing.
If you have one of these kits or
you're just here because you're
curious to see what the community
has made, I'm going to give a quick
tour of the board and some of the on-chip
projects, and show you how to get started.
So let's crack on!
A year ago I joined the "Zero to ASIC" course
hosted by Matt Venn, with the promise that for
a surprisingly low price, someone like me with no
prior experience could learn to design a chip --
an "ASIC" or "Application-Specific Integrated
Circuit" -- and actually get it manufactured.
Matt Venn also leads the "Tiny Tapeout"
program that enables the manufacturing,
and while I had just missed out on
joining this original "TT02" shuttle run,
it was exciting to watch Matt and the Tiny Tapeout
team do the world's first live chip bring-up,
and I joined the wait list to purchase one
of the few spare boards not already allocated
to the original contributors...
And that's what we have here now!
Taking a quick look at the board we see the
main ASIC: the crown jewel of custom-made
silicon which is mounted on a carrier
that acts as a breakout board, and that
is plugged into the demo board which provides
input, output, and some other basic control.
PCB manufacturing was made possible by the
sponsorship of a number of companies with
Efabless also facilitating the ASIC's manufacture.
The board design is by Pat Deegan of
Psychogenic Technologies and I must
say this kit looks and feels
pretty nice. So thanks Pat!
Okay let's get into it already! Time to
plug the board in and see what happens.
Use a USB-C cable just for power delivery.
Some future versions will also use it for
computer control. Straight away we see life.
From the factory these DIP switches select
the active design which we'll fiddle
with later. My board has design number
131 selected which is a simple "Hello,
World!" that we'll explore in a moment.
We see the "Power good" LEDs and a
flickering GPIO LED. An internal
CPU drives it but the designs themselves
are free-running hard circuits in silicon.
The 8 digital outputs from the chip each
drive a segment of this LED display,
which this design uses to display "HELLO",
albeit a bit fast out of the box. Note that
the outputs are also available on
the pins labeled "out0" to "out7".
Up here there is a jumper which connects an
onboard 20 MHz oscillator supplying the ASIC's
main system clock, and if we disconnect it we see
that the design freezes as well as the GPIO LED,
indicating a halt in the onchip CPU as well as
in the so-called "scan-chain" logic that links
all the designs. Replacing the jumper to the
same position lets everything carry on again.
The chip has 8 digital inputs which can
be turned on or off using the DIP switches
over here. Switching left is off; right
is on. As with the outputs these inputs
also have pins on the side labeled "in0" to
"in7". Just be aware that if you intend to
drive any externally their respective DIP
switches should be in the off position.
Up here is a reset button and a clock button,
each with a debouncing circuit to ensure clean
switching. The clock button is actually wired
directly to "in0" and the reset button to
"in1". In TT02 and 03 these signals are just by
convention and not all designs use them for the
same purposes. TT04 and above have dedicated
clock and reset lines and offer more I/O.
Here with the reset button pressed and
asserting the "in1" signal, this "Hello"
design actually uses the signal for its own clock
divider option, hence slowing it down a bit.
The clock button can be used to send individual
clock pulses via "in0" but with this "SLOW" jumper
connected, the ASIC is actually generating that
"in0" clock internally, itself. If we remove the
SLOW jumper, the GPIO LED keeps blinking but
the design halts, and the clock button would
now allow us to single-step the design's
clock if we wanted to control it directly.
Now let's explain how we can actually change
the generated slow clock signal by dividing
it. This is an important testing feature that is
part of the ASIC itself, not of this one design.
When replacing the SLOW jumper
or when powering up the board,
the rising edge on this "slow clock enable"
signal causes the binary number presented by
the input switches to be sampled and latched at
that moment, thus used as the input value for
the slow clock divider before the inputs
are then fed directly into the design.
In other words, if you were to turn on all
the switches and then replace the SLOW jumper,
the input value for the slow clock
divider would be the maximum of 255,
hence dividing the clock by 512,
to make it just under 10 Hz,
according to this formula as found
in the demo board's technical notes.
In this case our original slow clock divider
input was 128, to divide the clock by 258,
and I've now switched it to
254 to divide the clock by 510,
as we again place the slow clock jumper.
Switching all the inputs back to the normal
running state for this design, we see now
that it is approximately half the speed.
I'm going to count how many iterations the
design completes in 60 seconds. The design
goes through a total of 16 distinct states
and we can use a total count of iterations
in a given timeframe to calculate the
approximate slow clock rate. In this
case it's about 36 iterations so if we
divide that number by 60 seconds and
multiply it by the 16 states, we get pretty
close to the calculated slow clock of 9.8 Hz.
There are 161 distinct designs on this
chip so let's take a look at a couple
more that are easy enough to verify on this board.
Changing the project selection DIP switches
allows us to select the active design in real
time. The data sheet of each design shows you
how to set the project selection DIP switches.
Here I'm selecting design #0 which is a
straight-through inverter design. Each input
signal, if low, becomes a high output signal, and
vice versa. For my inputs in this case "in7" is
high, "in0" is being driven by the slow clock,
and all other inputs are low. As a result we see
the LED segment for "in0" blinking because of the
inverted slow clock, the dot is not lit because
it's the LED segment for "in7", and the rest
are lit up as the inverse of other low inputs.
Inputs would float when switched off but the
ASIC has enabled pull-down resistors internally.
By bad luck or maybe me being a bit rough,
my input DIP switches don't always fully
register the ON state so to work around this
I wired up some external DIP switches via the
input header pins, ran them through
a 1k 8-way resistor network to 3.3V,
and switched off all the input DIPs on the demo
board. These external DIP switches seem to do
the trick... and with that done, we now move on
to design #68 which is called "Breathing LED".
With this one I adjusted my camera to make the
effect more visible and I had to run the slow
clock at the full speed of 2500 Hz by ensuring all
input DIPs were off before power-up. This design
demonstrates PWM, or "pulse width modulation",
which can be seen as a gradual pulsating effect
on the top LED segment. All other LED segments
are showing the internal state of the PWM.
I've also hooked up my oscilloscope
to "out0" and we can see the slowly
increasing and decreasing duty cycle of the
PWM waveform that creates the pulsating effect.
Next up it's design #28, "Loading Animation".
This design is one of many on the chip that
was drawn out as a schematic using Wokwi, so you
can easily go and simulate it yourself online.
I've started up my slow clock at full speed
this time; the fixed appearance of the GPIO
LED is a clue of that. This design uses a
negative reset on "in1" so we switch it high
to let the design run, and an LED segment
slowly makes its way around the display.
If we switch on "in2" it appears to do
nothing now but this has actually disabled
the design's own clock divider, which means
it's running too fast to be seen. By flipping
a couple of the higher input switches and
toggling the "slow clock enable" jumper,
we can see the effect at more sensible
speeds... slow at about 12.5 Hz;
then a little faster at 18.7 Hz; and a
fair bit faster than that at 35.7 Hz.
How about a bit of sound now? Design #37,
"Siren", is meant to run at 12.5 kHz but
for now I'll be running it five times slower
at 2.5 kHz. Its audio output is "out7" and is
intended to drive a piezo speaker, but I've put
it through a simple resistor voltage divider so
it produces line-out levels to drive the
auxiliary input of an amplified speaker.
From power on it plays various tones and provides
a pretty display on the seven segment LEDs. I
would need to provide an external clock to
go faster than this but instead I've sped up
the footage by five times to demonstrate
how the design was intended to play out.
While I've given a brief overview of some of the
simpler designs on the TT02 ASIC there's plenty
more to be seen. Examples of more sophisticated
designs include: Design #36 which presents 1,000
digits of pi; design #2 which drives a character
LCD display; design #25 which transmits different
messages via UART signaling; design #75 which
is an internal high-speed ring oscillator;
many small CPU designs, some with SPI memory
access; some small scale implementations of FPGAs;
and many other visual and audio effects,
puzzles, controllers, and maths devices.
So what comes next? Well if there's
more you'd like to know about a
particular design or other features
of the ASIC or board, let me know.
If you've got a design on the TT02 chip, post a
comment to let me know and optionally discuss it,
or otherwise consider making a video
of your own. And be sure to jump into
the Tiny Tapeout Discord to discuss your findings.
If you'd like to be involved
in a future production run,
particularly as the technology
offering and tools improve,
check out tinytapeout.com, or see
the description of this video.
Please give this video a thumbs up if you found it
useful or if you find this new frontier exciting,
and if you would like to see
more chip design, electronics,
or my projects in general, please also
consider subscribing to my channel.
Looking forward I'm more interested in TT03
which should be coming soon with a doubled
clock and more designs including a tiny one of
my own, and then TT04 and 05 which are being
manufactured at the time of this recording. These
newer generations, including the upcoming TT06,
were recently teased with a prototype "TT03p5"
demo and offer options for more design area, a
lot more IO, bandwidth on the order of 30 MHz, and
analog and mixed-signal design support as of TT06.
Since discovering Tiny Tapeout and the Zero to
ASIC course, I'm addicted! I've got designs on all
of the Tiny Tapeout shuttles starting with TT03. I
think I've got a bit of a problem! But I love it!