Normally, making a
custom chip costs tens of
thousands of dollars,
and don't forget another
hundred thousand dollars for renting the
design software.
Oh, and you'll have to sign an NDA to
get started.
And that NDA means you can't share your
design with anyone.
Tiny Tapeout makes
it easier, quicker and
cheaper than ever before
to get your designs onto
a real chip. Open-source
tools, excellent
documentation, and a vibrant
community helps to make it
much easier to get started and avoid common
mistakes. Tiny Tapeout is for students,
makers, hackers, universities, and anyone
interested in learning
more or getting their designs
made into silicon. All
our learning resources
and tools are free to
use, and they're online to
avoid download,
installation, and licensing
problems. If you're a
total beginner, you can try
Wokwi, our digital
design and simulator tool.
Or if you know what
you're doing, you can use a
hardware description
language like Verilog, VHDL,
or Amaranth. Then, use
our GitHub action-based
system to build the files
you need for the ASIC.
Once the files are
ready, you can explore the
layout with this really
cool 3D viewer. The
minimum size is 160 x 100
microns, about a thousand
logic cells. And if you
need more space, you can
buy extra tiles. Each
design gets access to clock,
reset, and 24 I/Os, with
about 50 megahertz bandwidth.
Tiny tape out isn't
just for digital designs.
For Tiny Tapeout 6, we've
added analog and mixed
signal support, as well
as support for designs
made with proprietary
tools like Cadence. Once
the design is ready,
we send it to Efabless,
and they'll manufacture
it on the open-source
Skywater 130 nanometer
process. The first 100
submissions from
individuals will get an early
bird discount thanks
to Efabless sponsorship.
And I want to say a really
big thanks to Efabless
for sponsoring this project
and making it possible.
Once we get the silicon back, we save you
time and trouble by mounting the chip onto a
demonstration board.
After plugging the board into
your computer, you select
which design you want
to be active with our
MicroPython interface.
And that also lets you
adjust the clock speed,
set the inputs, and
monitor the outputs. One of
my favorite things
about this project is that
you're not only going
to get your design, but
everybody else's design
as well. You'll be able to
look through the chip
status sheet and try out
someone else's design.
In our previous runs,
we've seen some
really interesting designs,
including RISC-V CPUs,
FPGA's, ring oscillators,
synthesizers, USB devices, and lots more.
To get started, follow the video tutorials,
expect it to take between
a few hours and a few
weeks depending on how
complex your design is.
If you get stuck, join
our Discord community
chat. Make sure you
sign up to the mailing list to
keep up to date with our
progress. So have fun, get
involved, and I'm really
looking forward to seeing
what you make on your first ASIC.
(bright music)