In this video we're going to learn how
to use the Tiny Tapeout GitHub template
to turn your design into the ASIC files
we need to manufacture the chip.
If you don't already have a GitHub
account you'll need to create one.
Then navigate to one of the template
repositories. We have one for Wokwi
designs and another one for Verilog or
other HDLs.
I'll use the Wokwi template for now.
Click the "Use this template" button.
This creates your own copy of the
repository.
For open source projects GitHub pays for
the cloud compute which we use to make
the ASIC files.
It's turned on by default but we still
need to allow the actions to create the
results page.
We have the instructions here but I'll
show you how to do it now.
Go to your repository settings page,
"Pages", then set build and deploy source
to "GitHub actions".
Now we're ready to adapt the template to
our own projects by editing the info.yaml
file.
For Wokwi projects you need to change
the project's Wokwi ID to match the
number in your Wokwi project.
For HDL projects like Verilog or Amaranth
we use the source file section here.
That's covered in a separate video
called "Working with an HDL".
Okay so let's set the Wokwi ID to
match our project.
I'll copy the last part of the projects
URL and replace the 0 with it.
Most simple designs will fit into one
tile.
If you need more space you can change
the tile setting to get more space.
Bigger designs cost more.
If you're not sure just start with one
and see what happens.
We also need to fill out the title,
author and so on.
If you use Discord then put your Discord
name here and when you submit a design
we'll add you to the Tapeout role.
Further down in the file there's a
section to describe what the pins do.
And this is really useful for testing
other people's designs so please fill it
in.
Then hit the commit button to save your
changes.
There's one more file you have to edit,
the info.md inside the docs directory.
This is important for a few reasons.
First is that because everyone who
orders a chip will also get your design.
It's nice if they can understand how to
experiment with it.
The second reason is that by the time
the chips come back you'll probably have
forgotten how it works
and you'll be glad you wrote down some
instructions.
You can make the documentation better by
adding pictures and links to extra
documentation.
After filling in all the details press
the commit button.
This starts the GitHub actions running.
You can access the results using the
actions tab at the top here.
We have three actions.
One for documentation that shows how
your documentation will look when it's
printed
and other will be used for automatic
testing of what we designs if you've used
the truth table option.
And finally we have the GDS action which
is used to build the ASIC files for
manufacturing.
If you want to find out more about that
we have a separate video showing how it
works.
It's called how the GitHub action
creates the ASIC files.
Let's take a quick look at the docs
action.
This is useful to see how your
documentation will be formatted for the
online and print data sheet.
We get a PDF file we can download and
check to see if the formatting and the
picture works.
Let's take a look at the GDS action
results.
We have this nice page with some
warnings, utilization statistics and
standard cell usage.
If you don't understand a warning join
us on the Discord chat server and post in
the GitHub actions channel.
You can take a look at the cells in use
by clicking these links.
For example this X-NOR2 gate.
Let's take a closer look at the 3D
viewer.
Right click to pan, left click to change
the perspective, scroll wheel to zoom in
and out.
On the right we can see which cells are
used and how many, above we have the
control for layer visibility.
We also have some shortcut keys on the
right.
Pressing "1" hides all the filler cells,
"2" hides the wiring and "3" isolates
the currently selected cell.
I'd really appreciate it if you took a
screenshot of your design and posted it
on social media
with a description of what it does along
with a Tiny Tapeout hashtag.
Back on the front page of the repository
you'll see we have these three green
lights now for the docs, test and GDS all
passing.
The GDS status needs to be green to
submit your design.
Sometimes the GDS action will fail.
A Wokwi design should almost always
work.
If not then it's probably our problem
and you should let us know in the Wokwi
channel of the Discord chat server.
If you're using an HDL it's usually
because of an error in your design or
because the design is too large.
To get more details you can look at the
logs here in the action results or
download the zipped GDS logs out of
hacked and take a look inside.
First check the synthesis log file under
runs > wokwi > logs > synthesis > synthesis.errors for design errors.
If your design is too large then the
failure will normally be to do with the
placement or routing part of the flow.
You can try to reduce your design size
or upgrade to a larger design by
increasing the number of tiles in your
info.yaml config.
When you're ready to submit go to
tinytapeout.com and then scroll down to
the submission section.
Click the button to go to our submission
app.
Sign in with your GitHub account then
copy and paste the URL of your GitHub
repository into the form and press submit.
If you have a coupon you can apply it
here otherwise you'll need to pay to
continue.
At this point you've created your
project but it's not yet part of the Tiny Tapeout.
You have to submit a revision first.
Once that's happened that version of
your design is committed to the shuttle.
If you want to make any changes you need
to come back here and submit a new
revision.
So that's it. Happy hacking and I look
forward to seeing what you make on your
ASIC.
[Music]