In this video, we're going
to take a look at the GitHub
actions that produce the GDS
files we need for the Tapeout.
To show you this action, I'm going to be
using the Verilog demo.
The way that GitHub actions work is that
inside this special .github directory,
we have workflows.
They're written in YAML.
We have these three different files here,
and the most important one is the GDS.
This one creates a PDF, so you
can see what your page and the
datasheet will look like, and
this one runs an automatic test.
Let's take a look at the GDS action.
It starts with the name of the action,
and then specifies how it's to be run.
Either we can start it when
we push to the repository,
or workflow dispatch means
we can also start it manually.
Then the work is done down here in the
jobs section.
It specifies to use Ubuntu as an operating
system, and then we have two tasks,
GDS and viewer.
Each of those uses an
additional composite action
file that lives in the
Tiny Tapeout repository.
Let's take a look at the composite GDS
action.
We've got a bunch of environment variables
here that say what version of OpenLane
should be used, and where it
should be installed, along with
the variant of the PDK and
where that should be installed.
I'll briefly talk about OpenLane at the
end of this video.
Prerequisites are installed along with the
Tiny Tapeout support tools.
The user configuration
gets generated, which will
either fetch the Wokwi
net list or use the HDL files.
Then OpenLane is cloned
at a specific commit, and
the make command
installs it along with the PDK.
Then the TT tool is used to run OpenLane.
Let's take a look at that over here in the
TT support tools repository.
This starts the OpenLane
docker and gives it the right
commands and environment
settings to start the build.
Then we show you new warnings,
the routing and cell usage summary here.
These lines save the GDS and some
important logs to a downloadable artifact.
These lines create the PNG render of the
final GDS.
You can find out more about OpenLane here.
OpenLane is an open source RTL to GDS
flow.
It converts your design into the ASIC
files we need for manufacturing.
If you want to learn more, then consider
taking my amazing Zero-to-ASIC course,
which also covers digital design in
Verilog.