[Matt] And one last
thing that just came to
mind is we've got a
lot of people that
are planning to join
us to Tapeout on
Tiny Tapeout 2 and
the 60% of people
said that they were
interested in using
an HDL. So
presumably people
have come from doing
simulations or do it
probably using a bit
of FPGA work. So is
there any advice you
would give to
somebody who was
like converting an
FPGA design to an
ASIC design. I think
for me that like
the, the, the most
crucial one is with
FPGAs, you can
almost always
guarantee that the
registers are going
to get initialized
to zero. And you can
have these initial
begin blocks. [Guest: Yeah. So...]
So you have to have
a good reset that
sets everything to zero.
[Guest] Yeah yeah yeah. I mean I
think that's so the,
the presence of an
explicit reset on
the flip-flop that
actually needed for
the design to work
is something that I
recommend doing in
FPGA as well,
because even in
FPGA, even though
through, the registers
might be initial
labels will be
initialized to some
defined state after
configuration.
You know, if you use
a PLL or stuff like
that, your clock is
not stable at the
beginning, which
means technically
you can't start
clocking your logic
without failing,
without timing
violation. Which
means it's always a
good idea to hold
every critical flip-flop
in reset until the
PLL is locked,
which requires your
design to have an
explicit reset
anyway. Something
else that not shocks
me, but like it's
very different
between FPGA and and
in and ASIC design.
Is that in FPGA? You
know, you have you I
mean, typically you
have your Luts and a
register right
after. That's like
the typical
architecture which
means that you
pretty much get
registers for free.
Like, you can
heavily pipeline
your design, and it
doesn't cost you
that much because
the register is
there anyway. In
basic that's not the
case like this. If
you look at the
logic cell that
implement a register
versus the the, the
logic cells that
implement like an
end or like a logic
function. Yeah, the
registers is like
many times bigger,
which means that if
you heavily
pipeline, your
design is going to
explode in size.
And, you know, the
the logic delay
isn't that much, you
can get away with
much more logic
between your flip-flops than in
your FPGA.
Basically. That's
that's one that's
one of the things
when, when I, you
know, redesign stuff
for ASIC that I
change a lot is
because. Yeah, in in
FPGA I'm more
constrained
sometimes by the
speed, especially
since I work a lot
with ice40 and stuff
like that, which are
really slow FPGAs.
So I tend to
pipeline a lot. And
in ASIC design like
that, the design
size would explode.
So yeah. And then if
you fancy, you can
start playing with
latches instead of
flip-flop, but then
you really have to know
what you're doing. So,
[Matt] Maybe not good for
Tiny Tapeout. We'll see
what happens. [Guest: Yeah]
Well, we we did see
some interesting
submissions for Tiny
Tapeout 1.
Yeah, definitely.
Like from the back.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah.
[Matt] Okay. Well, thanks
very much for your
time. Really
appreciate it. And
[Guest: thank you for real]
See you. See you.
Hopefully. See you
soon.
[Guest] Yeah. See you soon.