Normally, making a custom chip costs
tens of thousands of dollars, and don't
forget another
hundred thousand dollars for renting the
design software.
Oh, and you'll have to sign an NDA to
get started.
And that NDA means you can't share your
design with anyone.
Tiny tape out makes it easier, quicker
and cheaper than ever before to get your
designs onto
a real chip. Open source tools,
excellent documentation, and a vibrant
community helps to make it
much easier to get started and avoid
common mistakes. Tiny tape out is for
students,
makers, hackers, universities, and
anyone interested in learning more or
getting their designs
made into silicon. All our learning
resources and tools are free to use, and
they're online to
avoid download, installation, and
licensing problems. If you're a total
beginner, you can try
Watquey, our digital design and
simulator tool. Or if you know what
you're doing, you can use a
hardware description language like
Verilog, DHDL, or Amaranth. Then, use our
GitHub action-based
system to build the files you need for
the ASIC. Once the files are ready, you
can explore the
layout with this really cool 3D viewer.
The minimum size is 160 x 100 microns,
about a thousand
logic cells. And if you need more space,
you can buy extra tiles. Each design gets
access to clock,
reset, and 24 IOs, with about 50
megahertz bandwidth. Tiny tape out isn't
just for digital designs.
For Tiny tape out 6, we've added analog
and mixed signal support, as well as
support for designs
made with proprietary tools like
cadence. Once the design is ready, we
send it to E-Fabless,
and they'll manufacture it on the open
source Skywater 130 nanometer process.
The first 100
submissions from individuals will get an
early bird discount thanks to E-Fabless
sponsorship.
And I want to say a really big thanks to
E-Fabless for sponsoring this project and
making it possible.
Once we get the silicon back, we save
you time and trouble by mounting the chip
onto a
demonstration board. After plugging the
board into your computer, you select
which design you want
to be active with our micro python
interface. And that also lets you adjust
the clock speed,
set the inputs, and monitor the outputs.
One of my favorite things about this
project is that
you're not only going to get your
design, but everybody else's design as
well. You'll be able to
look through the chip status sheet and
try out someone else's design. In our
previous runs,
we've seen some really interesting
designs, including risk 5 CPUs, FPGA's,
ring oscillators,
synthesizers, USB devices, and loads
more. To get started, follow the video
tutorials,
expect it to take between a few hours
and a few weeks depending on how complex
your design is.
If you get stuck, join our Discord
community chat. Make sure you sign up to
the mailing list to
keep up to date with our progress. So
have fun, get involved, and I'm really
looking forward to seeing
what you make on your first ASIC.
[music fades]