Normally, making a custom chip costs
tens of thousands of dollars,
and don't forget another hundred
thousand dollars for renting the design
software.
Oh, and you'll have to sign an NDA to
get started.
And by the way, that NDA means you can't
share your design with anyone.
Tiny Tape Out makes it easier, quicker,
and cheaper than ever before
to get your designs onto a real chip.
Open Source Tools, excellent
documentation, and a vibrant community
helps to make it much easier to get
started and avoid common mistakes.
Tiny Tape Out is for students, for
makers, hackers, universities,
and anyone who's interested in learning
more or getting their designs made into a
chip.
All our learning resources and tools are
free to use,
and they're online to avoid download and
installation problems.
If you're a total beginner, you can try
walkway,
our digital design and simulator tool.
Or if you know what you're doing, you
can use a hardware description language
like Verilog, VHDL, or Amaranth.
Then, use our GitHub Action-based system
to build the files you need for the ASIC.
This also lets you explore your design
with this really cool 3D viewer.
Once your design is finished, you can
make an order.
The minimum size is 160 by 100 microns,
and that's just $100 including a PCB.
If you need more space, you can buy
extra tiles for $50 each.
We also have special deals for group
workshops and universities.
You might be asking, how is it possible
to get the price so low?
The trick is that we combine all the
little projects into one big design
using our fast multiplexer.
160 by 100 microns doesn't sound like a
lot,
but in our three previous runs we've
seen a load of interesting designs made,
including risk-five CPUs, FPGAs, and
lots more.
One of my favourite things about this
project is that not only are you going to
get your design,
but you're going to get everybody else's
design as well.
You'll be able to look through the chips
data sheet and try out someone else's
design.
Our previous three runs all used a
slower scan chain,
so this is a really big upgrade.
We're now expecting around 50 megahertz
bandwidth on the I/O.
Another upgrade is that we've now got
more I/O.
We have clock, reset, 8 inputs, 8
outputs, and 8 by directional pins.
Once the design is ready, we send it to
eFabless,
and they'll manufacture it on the open
source Skywater 130nm process.
I want to say a really big thanks to
eFabless for sponsoring this project and
making it possible.
Once we get the silicon back, we save
you the trouble of soldering by mounting
it onto a PCB.
You select which design you want to be
active with these switches,
and then the multiplexer connects the
design to the inputs and the outputs.
To get started, follow the video
tutorials.
Expect it to take between a few hours
and a few weeks depending on how complex
you design it.
If you get stuck, join our Discord chat
server.
Make sure you sign up to the mailing
list so that you know when submission's
open.
So have fun, get involved, and I'm
really looking forward to seeing what you
make on it first ASIC.
[END PLAYBACK]