One of the exciting things about Tiny Tape
Out 6 is we've added support for analog
and mixed signal design, as well as
designs made by proprietary tools.
That's because every design now is power
gated, so even if you submitted a complete
short circuit, it wouldn't take down the
whole chip.
What I'm going to show you in this video
is how you can get started with a mixed
signal design or an analog design,
and I'm going to be using the Magic VLSI
tool that you could use KLayout or any
proprietary tool you want.
And I'm going to be taking you through the
steps to make a very simple design,
in this case, an R2R digital to analog
converter.
I'm not going to spend any time on the
schematic drawing, the simulation,
the parasitic extraction, the LVS.
I'm just going to show
you the flow that you need
to do to actually get a
design ready to submit.
So let's start off by taking a look at the
website.
At the moment, everything is on this
Techspecs analog pins page.
And there's a bit of information here
about how many pins you can have,
the specifications and limitations.
Biggest ones is limited to 1.8 volts and
you can't use metal 5.
We supply some templates that you can get
started with.
All the normal digital pins are on the top
and the analog pins are at the bottom.
You must have two power ports and they've
got to be named correctly on metal 4.
They both need to have the same width,
but there's some variance.
You're allowed in there and
then the pricing because we're
only allowing analog on the
top and the bottom of the chip.
And we've only got eight pins.
We're charging $40 per pin.
Okay, so let's move on for actually
creating and submitting an analog design.
So we're going to go to the template
repository.
Just like for digital designs and you use
this template button.
And call it something sensible or
ridiculous up to you.
And then we just download this,
clone it onto your workstation.
Unlike the digital flow, pretty much all
of this has to be done locally.
And I'm just going to start off by making
a mag for magic, GDS and left directories.
Now you've got to pick a template.
The minimum size is one by
two, but we also have bigger
ones if you want bigger
ones, bigger ones cost more.
And we're just going to get this template.
I download it with wget, paste that in
there.
So now I've got my def file.
And the next step is editing the info.yaml
file.
You want to pick a unique
name for the top level
and then you need
to be consistent with it.
And you also got to have title,
author and description.
Otherwise the documentation check will
fail.
It's a good idea to label your inputs.
We don't have any digital outputs and
we're not using bidirectional,
but we are using this one analog pin and
we'll delete the other one.
Only the pins you list here will actually
be connected.
And then edit the Verilog stub,
just got to match the name basically.
And then we need some documentation here.
OK, so as I mentioned,
I'm not going to spend time
on the all the details of
doing an analog design.
I've linked some resources.
We're going to use, I'm going
to use Magic to draw this out
and I'm going to get started
by using this Tcl script.
Which basically reads
the def template that you've
downloaded and then uses
that to create the top level shell.
And then draws the power and ground lines
and writes out the first GDS and left.
So to start up Magic,
got to use its correct RC
file and make sure that
matches with the PDK.
If things are working,
you'll have the palette on the
right and it will say Sky
130 technology in the top.
If those aren't there,
then you've got a problem
with your install that
needs to get sorted first.
And then we can run all those commands by
sourcing that Tcl script.
So if you're not using Magic,
you just need to make sure that
what happens with this Tcl
script happens in your tool.
But basically, it's just creating these
two power straps and naming.
The design and up here on the top, we've
got our inputs and down on the bottom.
We've got our analog pins.
And that is the ground pin.
And that's the power pin.
So now I've sped this bit up a lot, so
you're not bored by my terrible Magic skills.
And if you want to learn how to use Magic
or Klayout, then check some of the
resources listed in the analog pins page I
showed earlier.
And that's that for the schematic.
So I need to export the GDS in the left
now.
Just copy and paste that into the tickle
window.
Not sure if it did the GDS, so repeat
that.
And then check out the new files we've got
the GDS, we've got the left.
Take a look at the left, it's all the
pins.
Use K layout as an alternative GDS viewer.
Sanity check.
And then add everything.
Push that to our repo.
And then in the repo, we can check the
actions, which will be running now.
So I speed this up, it takes a few
minutes.
And we run a GDS check, basically check
that the DRC is fine.
Before we accept your
submission, so you can just take
a look at that by clicking
on here and scrolling down.
DRC, K layout.
And then we're going to make a new
submission.
So I'm going to
app.tinytapeout.com, ignore that
staging in the URL that's
just for me to do this test.
Create the project.
Pay for it.
Submit it.
And now we're on the, we reserved our
space, but we need to actually submit a
new revision to put it on, which does that
by creating a pull request.
And there we go, success.
So that's a very brief
overview of how to get
started with an analog
or mixed signal design.
If you get stuck anywhere, then reach out
to us on the analog channel in the Discord.
And I really look forward
to seeing some more mixed
signal and analog
designs on tiny tape out six.
So good luck and let us know how you get
on.