(Transcribed by Sonix.ai - Remove this message by upgrading your Sonix account) Normally, making a custom chip costs
tens of thousands of dollars. And
don't forget another $100,000 for
renting the design software. Oh, and
you'll have to sign an NDA to get
started. And by the way, that NDA
means you can't share your design
with anyone. Tiny Tapeout makes it
easier, quicker, and cheaper than
ever before to get your designs onto
a real chip. Open source tools,
excellent documentation, and a
vibrant community helps to make it
much easier to get started and avoid
common mistakes. Tiny Tapeout is for
students, for makers, hackers,
universities, and anyone who's
interested in learning more or
getting their designs made into a
chip. All our learning resources and
tools are free to use, and they're
online to avoid download and
installation problems. If you're a
total beginner, you can try walkway,
our digital design and simulator
tool. Or, if you know what you're
doing, you can use a hardware
description language like Verilog,
VHDL, or amaranth.
Then use our GitHub action based
system to build the files you need
for the ASIC. This also lets you
explore your design with this really
cool 3D viewer. Once your design is
finished, you can make an order. The
minimum size is 160 by 100 microns,
and that's just $100, including a
PCB. If you need more space, you can
buy extra tiles for $50 each. We
also have special deals for group
workshops and universities. You
might be asking, how is it possible
to get the price so low? The trick
is that we combine all the little
projects into one big design. Using
our fast multiplexer 160 by 100
microns doesn't sound like a lot,
but in our three previous runs we've
seen a load of interesting designs
made, including Risc-v CPUs, FPGAs,
and lots more. One of my favorite
things about this project is that
not only are you going to get your
design, but you're going to get
everybody else's design as well.
You'll be able to look through the
chip's data sheet and try out
someone else's design. Our previous
three runs all used a slower scan
chain, so this is a really big
upgrade. We're now expecting around
50MHz bandwidth on the I o. Another
upgrade is that we've now got more I
o. We have clock reset, eight
inputs, eight outputs and eight
bidirectional pins. Once the design
is ready, we send it to fabulous and
they'll manufacture it on the open
source Skywater 130 nanometer
process. I want to say a really big
thanks to fabulous for sponsoring
this project and making it possible.
Once we get the silicon back, we
save you the trouble of soldering by
mounting it onto a PCB. You select
which design you want to be active
with these switches, and then the
multiplexer connects the design to
the inputs and the outputs. To get
started, follow the video tutorials.
Expect it to take between a few
hours and a few weeks, depending on
how complex your design is. If you
get stuck, join our discord chat
server. Make sure you sign up to the
mailing list so that you know when
submissions open. So have fun, get
involved and I'm really looking
forward to seeing what you make on
your first ASIC.  (Transcribed by Sonix.ai - Remove this message by upgrading your Sonix account)