[Music]
So I finally finished my flip-flop
video, took a lot longer than I thought,
and that's because every time I try to record
the video, I get to this point and I realize
I still can't explain this bit, and I'd
have to go a little bit deeper, dig down
a bit,
and finally get the answer. And it's
been like that for quite a few days now.
I also want to say thanks to everyone on
the course, because it's your support
that lets me make these kinds of
deep-die videos to satisfy my curiosity.
So let's start off by looking at what's
going to be covered in this video.
So small text means we're not
going to spend too much time, and
big text is what the bulk of the
video is going to be spent on.
To give it a bit of a contextual overview, we're going
to look at Combinatory versus sequential circuits,
moving on to latches and flip-flops, and then the
majority of the time we're going to be looking at
how a flip-flop really works, why does
it set up a whole time come from,
what does a set up and hold violation
mean, and metastability.
So really maybe the first question is, why do we need flip-flops
in the first place? Why do we need sequential circuits?
So when we're designing digital logic,
whether it's for an FPGA or an ASIC,
the part of the circuit that is doing
the work, like an adder or a multiplier,
that's all built out of combinatorial logic, things like,
AND gates, OR gates, XORs, NOTs, these kinds of things.
And we have this big pile of
logic, we put the numbers in,
and then a short while later, as the data propagates through
that collection of cells, we get the answer out of the end.
Now imagine we're implementing a
filter, and we want to take that output,
and then run it back through the
multiplier a certain number of times.
If we just take the output
and route it back to the input,
we're going to get a weird condition, a race
condition, where the data is flowing round and round,
and we lose control of what's happening.
So what we've got to do is we've
got to catch that data as it comes out,
wait, and put it back in at the
beginning at the correct time,
and usually that's
coordinated with a clock.
So the types of circuits that can catch
the data and hold it until a clock comes
are called latches or flip-flops, and
they're used for sequencing data flow.
So one thing to bear in
mind is this is a huge topic.
In my reference book, the Weste Harris
book, it's a really big chunk of the book,
Chapter 7, all about sequencing,
and this is really just focusing on a single
type of flip-flop and looking at how it works.
So before we can make a
flip-flop, we need to make a latch.
So what is a latch?
Well, the simplest type of latch is just
a MOSFET with the D data coming in
and the Q data out going out,
and this allows the data to flow through
when the clock is high,
because it's an N channel MOSFET.
But it's got a lot of problems. It's not
immune to noise on the input.
It's a dynamic circuit, so the output is only
there because of capacitance on the wires.
So as time goes by, this one
value will degrade down to a zero.
We can improve the immunity
by having a transmission gate,
which is a P type and
an N type in parallel,
so it allows a 0 or a 1 through as
long as the clock is set correctly.
And then we can put a buffer at the end,
so that it can drive a bit harder,
have a bit more capacitance,
and store that dynamic value for longer.
And then we can build up to a latch
like this that has a feedback circuit
where the output of one inverter
drives the input of a tri-state inverter
and that comes back round
and reinforces the circuit,
and we can disconnect the
input with this transmission gate.
So if we take a quick look at this,
we've got this enable here with the
clock and the knock lock,
and that basically turns on or off the output
of this inverter that is on the outside.
So if we've got a 1 coming
in here, this is going to be off.
This is going to be on,
it's going to pull it down,
so the one is going to
get turned into a 0.
But only if these two
are also set correctly.
So by setting these on or off,
we can make this turn on or off.
That's what a tri-state inverter.
And you'll see as we move on in the video
that we're going to use a pair of latches
to build a flip-flop.
So now we get on to
what flip-flops actually are.
They're a way of sampling a
bit of data as the clock comes in
and then holding it steady, no
matter what the D input is doing,
and wait until the
next rising clock edge.
And there's a wide variety of flip-flops.
So there's an interesting paper here
that was recommended by a friend,
and we've got different types like
inverting outputs with reset,
resampling on the rising or falling edge,
different setup and hold times,
resulting in different aperture sizes,
power consumption, and
different things like this.
So this paper does quite a good job of comparing a
whole different type of flip-flops against each other
and then choosing the most
recommended one for the best immunity,
the best immunity to raise
conditions that least power consumed,
these kinds of things.
So what would an ideal flip-flop be like?
Remember we're going to be
using these to sequence data.
So the more time we spend
capturing and holding onto that data,
the less time we've
got to actually do work.
So an ideal flip-flop
should sample immediately.
The output should
immediately flow to the output,
and it should take hardly
any time to do the sampling.
There should be no
ambiguity on the output.
It should either always be 0 or 1,
and it should always sample
exactly on the clock edge,
or maybe we can move it
forwards and backwards,
but it's a very predictable time.
So I've got a background in
engineering and science communication
and my engineering background is one of the
things that makes me love a practical example.
And that's one reason why I think this
Sky130 open source PDK is so good
because it allows me to share this kind
of information with real-world examples
without having to sign,
NDAs, or ask for permission.
So I'm going to use some
Verilog to describe some hardware,
because that's what Verilog is,
hardware description language,
and I'm going to say on
the positive edge of a clock,
sample the D and put it into Q,
and Q should be a register.
You should remember what it is.
And when I run that through
OpenLane, I get a D type flip-flop.
And when I take my GDS
and I load that up in K layout,
I get this, which is a fairly
complicated standard cell.
It's quite a big one.
Every time polysilicon overlaps
some of the P type or N type,
that's the kind of cyan or
gray there, we get a MOSFET.
So we've got 26 different MOSFETs here.
A range in a fairly complicated pattern,
and that builds up half-flop.
So when I want to really
understand something,
especially like a standard cell, I like
to try and do a manual circuit extraction
to pull out all those connections
onto a piece of paper.
And this took me quite a long time,
much longer than the MUX example,
but I did a few videos back.
And you can see, actually here,
I thought I'd done where I had an
inverter followed by transmission gates.
But actually, it's a tri-state inverter,
which is a slightly different structure.
So this is the final extraction,
which I'm fairly sure is correct.
And then I got some help from Proppy on
the course
to make a nice neat schematic using
Schemdraw python library
and Maximo did this cool render.
So we've got the positive supply, the
negative supply,
and we've got the D input inverter here.
And then for our clock, we're taking a
clock in
and then generating an inverted and an
inverted-inverted clock.
So that's happening here and being
distributed
to the transmission gates here.
And over this side, we're looking at the
output,
which is a double-ganged inverter.
So we've got a two-time striped strength.
So how does a flip-flop flop?
Well, let's take a look at
the circuit in a bit more detail.
I've taken this top circuit
and then worked out
what happens for the transmission gates
when the clock is low or
high and then kind of drawn out
these two separate circuits.
So we start off when the clock is low.
The output is steady and it's isolated
because you've got this
one bit of data, a 0 or 1,
reinforcing itself,
this static memory
being driven output to Q.
And the input is kind
of sampling all the time.
Whatever is on D is inverted
and then is charging up A.
And at the moment
when the clock goes high,
this transmission gate opens and the one
that creates the first
latch inverter closes.
And so whatever was on A
is now going to get reinforced
in this loop, the input's
going to get ignored
and the output is going
to go straight out to Q.
So we have this race condition
between the data coming in and the clock.
If the data is changing at
the moment when we sample,
we could have something
that isn't exactly a 0 or a 1
on here and that can cause problems.
So this is what leads
us onto a metastability
So we have our zero state, a zero volts
and our one state, a 1.8 volts.
And those are both stable.
It takes work to change those values
and get them to over the hill
and change to the other one.
But let's say that the
D input was changing
and it was exactly 0.9 volts at
the moment the clock went high.
Then we start off
right at this top position,
which is a meta-stable place.
It doesn't really want to stay there.
It can move off from
one side to the other.
But it will stay there for
a lot longer than normal.
Then some fluctuation in the power supply
or something like that changes
and we flip into one
of these other states.
And another way to visualize
this is with a simulation.
So a friend of mine did the simulation
where he took these two
inverters in a feedback loop.
And then this is the current.
It takes to force it from
a zero to one state.
So if we square that, we get the power.
And you can see we have to do this work.
We have to put work in to go up the hill.
And then when we're
balanced on the top of the hill,
we just stay there.
And then the ball can stay there
for some long amount of time,
longish amount of time
until something knocks us off.
And then we plot back
into the other state.
So depending on where we start here,
if we start here, we're going
to fall down fairly quickly
back to one state.
If we start here, we're going
to fall down to the other state.
But if we start up here, it takes a
longer time to fall down.
And if we start right in the middle,
it can take a really long time.
And when I say a long
time, I mean picoseconds.
So now to get a bit of a feel of
what these lengths of times are
and what the waveforms look like
and have a bit of an interactive play,
I developed this tool
that lets me scrub through
a whole bunch of simulations.
So I'm using Ngspice to run a loop
as the D pulse gets moved
closer and closer to the clock
and then through the clock
and then out of the clock.
And then we can turn
on and off all the signals
and have a look at how
they interact with each other.
So if you want to follow
along, you can clone the repo,
unzip the demo data set
that I have included in that
and then run the GUI.
If you've got the PDK installed locally,
you can just run the simulation
and then you can also tweak the SPICE deck
and get different results.
So when you start up the
program, it's going to look like this.
We can move the data pulse
through into the sampling window
and see how the output
changes from a low to a high.
And then as we keep moving,
it samples low again,
the output goes low.
And we've got the schematic down here
and we can turn on and
off these different waves
to get a better understanding.
So for example, we could look
at how the clock gets inverted
and double-inverted
and we can move in here
and we can use these
bars to measure the time.
So let's just do that quickly.
We're going to measure
from the 50% point,
to the 50% point.
So that's two inverters and
that's about 70 piece per second.
So it's taken about 35 picoseconds
to go through each inverter.
And that's the time between
the non-inverted clock
and then going re-inverted
and then uninverted again.
Now let's zoom in on that region
where the signal has to stay still
and see what happens
if it doesn't stay still.
See what happens to the output.
As that signal starts changing
within the setup and hold
window, the aperture of the flip-flop,
the output is taking
longer and longer to settle.
So what we could do is turn on a
couple of these other waveforms
and get a bit of a closer glimpse inside
and turn off that inverted clock.
And you can see how it takes
so much longer to settle down
than it does when we're
outside a sampling window.
And now maybe it's a good time to say
that this is one simulation
from the typical, typical corner
which means it's maybe
in the middle of the die
where everything is
working fairly correctly.
But you get these different corners,
these different types of simulations
for lower voltage, higher voltage,
faster MOSFETs, slower MOSFETs.
And so if you want to know
the worst case of something,
you've got to make sure that
you're using the right corner
to simulate.
And all that data gets
dumped into a Liberty file
and that file is what's actually used
to do the static timing analysis
that you would use to
check that your design
was actually going to
work and satisfy timing.
You may be familiar
with this timing diagram,
typical for a flip-flop where
we've got the clock with sampling.
We've got to keep the data
steady in the set of and hold times
and then we've got
some time for the output
to settle into the new value.
So let's measure what these
values are using the tool.
And we'll start off with TCQ,
the time between the clock
and the Q.
Let me turn off these signals.
So here we've got the clock.
Here we've got the Q.
So let's make sure
that's nice and stable.
Put that there.
And what I'm doing is I'm moving
the markers to their 50% point.
That's 0.9 volts.
And we're measuring 170 pico seconds.
I've got to lose the wrong way around.
So that's TCQ.
Now how do we measure this setup time?
So we do this by saying that we take TCQ
and we say 5% more
of that time is acceptable.
So about 180 picoseconds.
And then we find the point
where D is to make the TCQ extend
that much longer and
we call that the setup time.
So let's measure it.
So first I'll move this to
180 picoseconds down here.
And then I'll move D in
until I get to that point.
Zoom in a little bit maybe.
About there.
And then what I'll do is
I'll measure this distance
between these two here.
So I'll move this one here.
And this one there.
50% point.
And I've got about 67 picoseconds.
So that's our setup.
About 70 picoseconds.
Now let's measure the hold.
And what I can do is we
need to see this edge changing.
So I can bring back through
the other side of the waveform
so that the output starts going low.
Do the same thing.
Move this to there we go.
170.
And then move it to 180 picoseconds.
And then find the time of the data where
I'm on that.
50% mark again.
About there.
And then again I'm going to
move this to the 50% point.
And we're measuring about 20 picoseconds.
But what do you notice
different about this waveform
that we're seeing here
compared to the one
that I showed you before?
Here the hold is positive
and extends this way.
But because the hold
window is now before the clock
we call this a negative hold.
And so really it would be better if
I had these the other way around.
So if it was after if it was over here
I would have a positive number.
But because it's behind
in front of the clock
I've got minus 20 picoseconds.
So it's set up is the time that
the signal has to be steady
in front of the clock signal.
And hold is the time the signal has to
be steady after the clock signal.
And as you've just seen with the sky 130
flip-flop
the hold time can be negative and that
means the whole aperture
is shifted in front of the clock.
So we can move that aperture backwards
by delaying the clock
with respect to the data.
And we can do that by tweaking the sizes
of the MOSFETs in use
while we're building the flip-flop.
But this window the aperture stays a
constant width.
So as we move it backwards we have the
effect of increasing the setup time.
So we have less time to do the work for
the digital logic.
So now let's see how setup and hold
impacts us as digital designers.
One of the important questions we want
to know is
how much time can we spend doing useful
computation
and how much time do we lose by having
to keep the data steady
during the setup and hold period.
So for setup we can say we have this
worst case condition
where we've got data coming out of one
flip-flop
through some combinatorial logic that
takes some time
and into a second flip-flop.
And here we've got a rising clock edge.
We've got Tcq the time it takes for
the data to come out of the flip-flop.
The amount of time it takes the logic to
do its work.
And then that data has got to be steady
and not moving the setup window.
And this amount of time here is the
slack.
The time we have left over to do extra
work.
So we can write that out as an equation.
The clock period always got to be more
than Tcq
plus the logic delay plus the setup time.
And an interesting thing to notice about
this equation
is that it involves the clock period.
So it's say we did have a problem with
the data changing in the setup time.
We could fix that just by increasing the
clock period
by decreasing the frequency
and that would bring that changing data
out of the setup time
and then our problem would go away.
We wouldn't get net stability anymore.
Another important question is how
quickly can the data start changing
after we get the clock and that's
related to the whole time.
So if we take our worst case this time
we've got the data coming into a
flip-flop
and then immediately out into the next
maybe for example in a shift register.
And we want to know if we're going to
get a problem
with the data changing within the whole
time of the second flip-flop.
So we've seen this Tcq
and if this is happening within the
whole window
then we're going to get a metastability
problem.
So the equation here is quite simple.
Tcq has always got to be bigger than
hold.
And it's interesting to note here that the
clock period is not part of this equation.
Tcq and the hold time are both
parameters of a flip-flop
and can't be changed later.
So that's why hold time violations are
so scary
because we can't fix them after a
takeout.
And that's one reason why flip-flops
have this negative hold
because it means that that equation can
never be true
and we'll never get hold violations.
So it's true that we lose time
because we remember the aperture is
staying the same size
we're just shifting it forwards.
So we lose time that we can be using for
computation.
It's as if we've got the bigger setup
time.
But because we really want to avoid the
possibility of hold violations
we're willing to sacrifice that extra
time.
So given that the Sky130 D-Type flop has
a negative hold time
how is it possible that MPW1 failed with
hold violations?
So to give you time to think I'm going
to play this awesome render
of a flip-flop doing its work done by
Maximo Balestrini
Well you probably saw my MPW1 fail vid so
you already know the answer to this question
but the answer is it's to do with clock
skew.
So before we were assuming that both
flip-flops had exactly the same clock
but if we have two different clocks then
basically all our plans go out the window
and we can end up with data changing
within either the setup or the hold time.
And the problem with MPW1 was that the
clock tree was synthesized badly
and we had so much skew across the chip
that we ended up with hold violations.
So to summarize the Sky130 flop is a
transmission gate flip flop
which according to the Berkeley paper is a
good compromise on power and race immunity
and it's got some nice graphs in the
rest of the paper.
You can have a look at if you want to
understand even deeper.
So I'd like to say again thanks to the
Zero-To-ASIC Course Community
to the anonymous ASIC Engineer who
helped to review the slides
and come up with the idea in the first
place.
Stefan Schippers for some input on Spice
modeling.
And for resources, Colin O'Flynn's
Metasibility demo on an FPGA is pretty good.
Shawn Hymel just got an FPGA series out with
DigiKey and the latest one talks about Metastability.
And of course you can get lots more information
and learn how to design chips yourself
on the Zero-To-ASIC Course.
So thanks for watching the video and
stay tuned for the next one.
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]