In this video you're
going to learn how to use
Wokwi to draw and simulate
simple digital designs.
After you open the template you
can minimize this area over here.
Left click and drag to move around.
Scroll wheel to zoom in and
out. I also like to turn the grid on.
We have two modes in Wokwi, drawing and
simulation. We'll start off by looking at drawing.
To add more logic gates you can use the plus button, then
start typing logic and you'll see all the available gates.
You can select a component and drag it.
The wires will stay connected.
You can adjust the wires by clicking
them and using the handles.
You can also change the colors. For neat
wiring you can click waypoints as you draw.
To copy a component select it and press D. To
copy a group of components including their wires
select them with shift, left click and drag. Then press D. Use
the delete key to delete components or groups of components.
Control Z and control
Y for undo and redo.
For more Wokwi tips check the FAQ here.
It's possible to create a bad circuit. For
example by connecting two outputs together
or making a short circuit. If that happens you'll get
an ERC box up here and you'll have to solve it before
your design can be made. Now we'll simulate
the design by clicking the green play button.
You can click individual switches but if you select
the whole switch you can also use your computer
keyboard to toggle the switches. You can see
how the output changes as I change the input.
For clock designs you can use our automatic clock
generator. With the switch this way the clock
will be running freely. Like this we can click
the button to create a single clock step.
For more information about the clock check the
FAQ. A little debug tip I like is to add an LED
to important parts of the circuit. That can help
you understand what's going on inside a circuit.
A nice feature for testing is creating a truth
table. If you create a new file on the left
called truthtable.md you can create a truth
table that will then be used to test your design.
For documentation on how it works read the
documentation here. Only logic gates that are connected
between the input and output boards are used. You
can leave any extra debugging LEDs or extra circuit
elements outside of the input and output
boards. They'll be ignored by the ASIC tools.
Make sure you save a copy of your design.
You'll get a new number in the URL here and that's
the number you need to submit to get your design
manufactured. To learn more about digital
design you can follow our lessons here.